Foreword

When it comes to learning a foreign language, relying on a set of textbooks or spending time in the classroom is not nearly enough. Memory is eroded by time; you keep forgetting what you have learned. Haven't we all been frustrated by our inability to remember new vocabulary? You learn a word and quickly forget it, so next time when you come across it you have to look it up in a dictionary. Only then do you realize that you used to know it, and you start to blame yourself, “why am I so forgetful?” when in fact, it's not your shaky memory that's at fault, but the fact that unless you review constantly, what you've learned quickly becomes dormant. The Chinese Breeze graded series is designed specially to help you remember what you've learned.

Everyone learning a second language has his or her way of jogging his or her memory. For example, some people make index cards or vocabulary notebooks so as to thumb through them frequently. Some simply try to go through dictionaries and try to memorize all the vocabulary items from A to Z. This spirit is laudable, but it is a painful process, and the results are far from sure. Chinese Breeze is a series of graded readers purposely written by professional authors. Each reader not only incorporates all the vocabulary and grammar specific to the grade but also contains an interesting and absorbing plot. They enable you to refresh and reinforce your knowledge and at the same time have a pleasurable time with the story. If you make Chinese Breeze a constant companion in your studies of Chinese, you won't have to worry about forgetting your vocabulary and grammar. You will also develop your feel for the language and root it firmly in your mind.

Thanks are due to Nyan-ping Bi, Xianmin Liu, and Ping Wei for arranging more than sixty students to field-test several of the readers in the Chinese Breeze series. Professor Tao-chung Yao at the University of Hawaii. Ms. Yu Li and Ph.D. students Ann Kelleher and Nicole Richardson of UC Davis provided very good editorial suggestions. We thank our colleagues, students, and friends for their support and assistance.

为所有中文学习者（包括华裔子弟）编写的
第一套系列化、成规模、原创性的大型分级轻松泛读丛书

“汉语风”（Chinese Breeze）分级系列读物简介

“汉语风”（Chinese Breeze）是一套大型中文分级泛读系列丛书。这套丛书以“学习者通过轻松、广泛的阅读提高语言的熟练程度，培养语感，增强对中文的兴趣和学习自信心”为基本理念，根据难度分为8个等级，每一级6—8册，共近60册，每册8,000至30,000字。丛书的读者对象为中文水平从初级（大致掌握300个常用词）一直到高级（掌握3,000—4,500个常用词）的大学生和中学生（包括修美国AP课程的学生），以及其他中文学习者。

“汉语风”分级读物在设计和创作上有以下九个主要特点：

一、等级完备，方便选择。精心设计的8个语言等级，能满足不同程度的中文学习者的需要，使他们都能找到适合自己语言水平的读物。8个等级的读物所使用的基本词汇数目如下：

第1级：300基本词 | 第5级：1,500基本词
第2级：500基本词 | 第6级：2,100基本词
第3级：750基本词 | 第7级：3,000基本词
第4级：1,100基本词 | 第8级：4,500基本词

为了选择适合自己的读物，读者可以先看看读物封底的故事介绍，如果能读懂大意，说明有能力读那本读物。如果读不懂，说明那本读物对你太难，应选择低一级的。读懂故事介绍以后，再看一下书后的生词总表，如果大部分生词都认识，说明那本读物对你太容易，应试着阅读更高一级的读物。

二、题材广泛，随意选读。丛书的内容和话题是青少年学生所喜欢的侦探历险、情感恋爱、社会风情、传记写实、科幻恐怖、神话传说等等。学习者可以根据自己的兴趣爱好进行选择，享受阅读的乐趣。

三、词汇实用，反复重现。各等级读物所选用的基础词语是该等级的学习者在中文交际中最需要最常用的。为研制“汉语风”各等级的基础词表，“汉语风”工程首先建立了两个语料库：一个是大规模的当代中文书面语和口语语料库，一个是以世界上不同地区有代表性的40余套中文教材为基础的教材语言库。然后根据不同的交际语域和使用语体对语料样本进行分层标注，再根据语言学习的基本阶程对语料样本分别进行分层统计和综合统计，最后得出符合不同学习阶程需要的不同的词汇使用度表，以此作为“汉语风”等级词表的基础。此外，“汉语风”等级词表还参考了美国、英国等国和中国大陆、台湾、香港等地所建的10余个当代中文语料库的词语统计结果。以全新的理念和方法研制的“汉语风”分级基础词表，力求既具有较高的交际实用性，也能与学生所用的教材保持高度的相关性。此外，“汉语风”的各级基础词语在读物中都通过不同的语境反复出现，以巩固记忆，促进语言的学习。

四、易读易懂，生词率低。“汉语风”严格控制读物的词汇分布、语法难度、情节开展和文化负荷，使读物易读易懂。在较初级的读物中，生词的密度严格控制在不构成理解障碍的1.5%到2%之间，而且每个生词（本级基础词语之外的词）在一本读物中初次出现的当页用脚注做出简明注释，并在以后每次出现时都用相同的索引序号进行通篇索引，篇末还附有生词总索引，以方便学生查找，帮助理解。

五、作家原创，情节有趣。“汉语风”的故事以原创作品为主，多数读物由专业作家为本套丛书专门创作。各篇读物力求故事新颖有趣，情节符合中文学习者的阅读兴趣。丛书中也包括少量改写的作品，改写也由专业作家进行，改写的原作一般都特点鲜明、故事性强，通过改写降低语言难度，使之适合该等级读者阅读。

六、语言自然，地道有味。读物以真实自然的语言写作，不仅避免了一般中文教材语言的枯燥和“教师腔”，还力求鲜活地道。

七、插图丰富，版式清新。读物在文本中配有丰富的、与情节内容自然融合的插图，既帮助理解，也刺激阅读。读物的版式设计清新大方，富有情趣。

八、练习形式多样，附有习题答案。读物设计了不同形式的练习以促进学习者对读物的多层次理解；所有习题都在书后附有答案，以方便查对，利于学习。

九、配有录音，两种语速选择。各册读物所附的故事录音（MP3格式），有正常语速和慢速两种语速选择，学习者可以通过听的方式轻松学习、享受听故事的愉悦。故事录音可通过扫描封底的二维码获得，也可通过网址http://www.pup.cn/dl/newsmore.cfm?sSnom=d203 下载。

For the first time ever, Chinese has an extensive series of enjoyable graded readers for non-native speakers and heritage learners of all levels

ABOUT Hànyǔ Fēng (Chinese Breeze)

Hànyǔ Fēng (Chinese Breeze) is a large and innovative Chinese graded reader series which offers nearly 60 titles of enjoyable stories at eight language levels. It is designed for college and secondary school Chinese language learners from beginning to advanced levels (including AP Chinese students), offering them a new opportunity to read for pleasure and simultaneously developing real fluency, building confidence, and increasing motivation for Chinese learning. Hànyǔ Fēng has the following main features:

☆ Eight carefully graded levels increasing from 8,000 to 30,000 characters in length to suit the reading competence of first through fourth-year Chinese students:

Level 1: 300 base words | Level 5: 1,500 base words
Level 2: 500 base words | Level 6: 2,100 base words
Level 3: 750 base words | Level 7: 3,000 base words
Level 4: 1,100 base words | Level 8: 4,500 base words

To check if a reader is at one's reading level, a learner can first try to read the introduction of the story on the back cover. If the introduction is comprehensible, the leaner will be able to understand the story. Otherwise the learner should start from a lower level reader. To check whether a reader is too easy, the learner can skim the Vocabulary (new words) Index at the end of the text. If most of the words on the new word list are familiar to the learner, then she/ he should try a higher level reader.

☆ Wide choice of topics, including detective, adventure, romance, fantasy, science fiction, society, biography, mythology, horror, etc. to meet the diverse interests of both adult and young adult learners.

☆ Careful selection of the most useful vocabulary for real life communication in modern standard Chinese. The base vocabulary used for writing each level was generated from sophisticated computational analyses of very large written and spoken Chinese corpora as well as a language databank of over 40 commonly used or representative Chinese textbooks in different countries.

☆ Controlled distribution of vocabulary and grammar as well as the deployment of story plots and cultural references for easy reading and efficient learning, and highly recycled base words in various contexts at each level to maximize language development.

☆ Easy to understand, low new word density, and convenient new word glosses and indexes. In lower level readers, new word density is strictly limited to 1.5% to 2%. All new words are conveniently glossed with footnotes upon first appearance and also fully indexed throughout the texts as well as at the end of the text.

☆ Mostly original stories providing fresh and exciting material for Chinese learners (and even native Chinese speakers).

☆ Authentic and engaging language crafted by professional writers teamed with pedagogical experts.

☆ Fully illustrated texts with appealing layouts that facilitate understanding and increase enjoyment.

☆ Including a variety of activities to stimulate students' interaction with the text and answer keys to help check for detailed and global understanding.

☆ Audio files in MP3 format with two speed choices (normal and slow) accompanying each title for convenient auditory learning. Scan the QR code on the backcover, or visit the website http://www.pup.cn/dl/newsmore.cfm?sSnom=d203 to download the audio files.

“汉语风”系列读物其他分册
Other Chinese Breeze titles

“汉语风”全套共8级近60册，自2007年11月起由北京大学出版社陆续出版。下面是已经出版或近期即将出版的各册书目。请访问北京大学出版社网站（www.pup.cn）关注最新的出版动态。

Hànyǔ Fēng (Chinese Breeze) series consists of nearly 60 titles at eight language levels. They have been published in succession since November 2007 by Peking University Press. For most recently released titles, please visit the Peking University Press website at www.pup.cn.

第1级：300词级
Level 1: 300 Word Level

两个想上天的孩子
Two Children Seeking the Joy Bridge

“叔叔，在哪里买飞机票？”

“小朋友，你们为什么来买飞机票？要去旅行吗？”

“不是。”“我们要到天上去。”

……

这两个要买飞机票的孩子，一个7岁，一个8岁。没有人知道，他们为什么想上天。这两个孩子也不知道，在他们出来以后，有人给他们的家里打电话，让他们的爸爸妈妈拿钱去换他们呢……

“Sir, where is the air-ticket office?”

“You two kids come to buy air-tickets? Are you gonna travel somewhere?”

“Nope. ”“We just wanna go up to the Joy Bridge.”

“The Joy Bridge?”

...

Of the two children at the airport to buy air-tickets, one is 7 and the other is 8. Beyond their wildest imaginings, after they ran away, their parents were called by some crooks who demanded a ransom to get them back...

我一定要找到她……
I Really Want to Find Her...

那个女孩儿太漂亮了，戴伟、杰夫和秋田看到了她的照片，都要去找她！照片是老师死前给他们的，可是照片上的中国女孩儿在哪儿？他们都不知道。最后，他们到中国是怎么找到那个女孩儿的？女孩儿又和他们说了什么？

She is really beautiful. Just one look at her photo and three guys, Dai-wei, Jie-fu and Qiu-tian, are all determined to find her! The photo was given to them by their professor before he died. And nobody knows where in China the girl is. How can the guys find her? And what happens when they finally see her?

我可以请你跳舞吗?
Can I Dance with You?

一个在银行工作的男人，跟他喜欢的女孩子刚认识，可是很多警察来找他，要带他走，因为银行里的一千万块钱不见了，有人说是他拿走的。

但是，拿那些钱的不是他，他知道是谁拿的。可是，他能找到证据吗？这真太难了。还有，以后他还能和那个女孩子见面吗？

A smart young man suddenly gets into big trouble. He just fell in love with a pretty girl, but now the police come and want to arrest him. The bank he works for lost 10 million dollars, and the police list him as a suspect.

Of course he is not the robber! He even knows who did it. But can he find evidence to prove it to the police? It's all just too much. Also, will he be able to see his girlfriend again?

向左向右
Left and Right: The Conjoined Brothers

向左和向右是两个男孩子的名字，爸爸妈妈也不知道向左是哥哥还是向右是哥哥，因为他们连在一起，是一起出生的连体人。他们每天都一起吃，一起住，一起玩儿。他们常常都很快乐。有时候，弟弟病了，哥哥帮他吃药，弟弟的病就好了。但是，学校上课的时候，他们在一起就不方便了……

Left and Right are two brothers. Even their parents don't know who is older and who is younger, as they are Siamese twins. They must do everything together. They play together, eat together, and sleep together. Most of the time they enjoy their lives and are very happy. When one was sick, the other helped his brother take his medicine and he got better. However, it's no fun anymore when they sit in class together but one brother dislikes the other's subjects...

你最喜欢谁？
Whom Do You Like More?

谢红去了外国，她是方新喜欢的人，可是方新不想去外国，因为他要在中关村做他喜欢的工作。小月每天来看方新，她是喜欢方新、也能帮方新的人，可是方新还是想着谢红。方新真不知道应该怎么办……

Xie Hong, Fang Xin's true love, has gone abroad to fulfill her dream. But Fang Xin only wants to stay in Zhongguancun in Beijing doing work that he enjoys. Xiao-yue comes to visit Fang Xin every day. She is the one who really understands Fang Xin. She loves him and can offer him the help that he badly needs. But only Xie Hong is in Fang Xin's mind. What should Fang Xin do? He seems to be losing his way in life...

第2级：500词级
Level 2: 500 Word Level

电脑公司的秘密
Secrets of a Computer Company

我家的大雁飞走了
Our Geese Have Gone

青凤
Green Phoenix

如果没有你
If I Didn't Have You

妈妈和儿子
Mother and Son

出事以后
After the Accident

一张旧画儿
An Old Painting

第3级：750词级
Level 3: 750 Word Level

第三只眼睛
The Third Eye

画皮
The Painted Skin

留在中国的月亮石雕
The Moon Sculpture Left Behind

朋友
Friends

第4级：1,100词级
Level 4: 1,100 Word Level

好狗维克
Vick the Good Dog

两件红衬衫
Two Red Shirts